Inventory of the Thomas E. Pugh Papers 1916-1999
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Thomas E. Pugh Papers 1916-1999
Special Collections Research Center
01/Mss. Acc. 1999.07
13.00
The papers of Rev. Thomas E. Pugh, a minister of the Williamsburg Baptist Church in Williamsburg, Virginia from 1952-1981.
Thomas E. Pugh, 1917-2006; Williamsburg Historic Records Association (Williamsburg, Va.) arrangement
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
The materials were acquired by Special Collections Research Center from Thomas Pugh and Mark Pugh. on 03/25/1999.
Biographical Note
Thomas E. Pugh was born on November 9, 1917 in Spotsylvania County, Virginia and died June 17, 2006 in Williamsburg, Virginia.
Pugh was pastor of Williamsburg Baptist Church for 29 years, 1952-1981. His tenure was the longest in the history of the church. When he retired, Pugh was named pastor emeritus.
When Pugh accepted the pastor position, one of his objectives was to embrace the students of the College of William and Mary. He sought to provide a ministry which would aid in their development during the formative college years.
Outside of the church community, Pugh served many organizations such as the American Red Cross and the Rotary Club. One of his most significant contributions to the Williamsburg community was his 25 year membership on the board of the Williamsburg Community Hospital.
Further information about this individual or organization may be available in the Special Collections Research Center Wiki
Scope and Contents
The papers of Rev. Thomas E. Pugh, a minister of the Williamsburg Baptist Church in Williamsburg, Virginia from 1952-1981.
Collection includes sermons, church bulletins, scrapbooks, correspondence, essays, other writings, and photographs encompassing both the business and personal life of Rev. Thomas Pugh. Box 8 includes a genealogical lineage of the Pugh Family.
Arrangement of Materials
Each accession is arranged separately, though most accessions have only been partially processed with a detailed list of contents.
Additional Information
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Williamsburg Baptist Church (Williamsburg, Va.)
Genre/Form of Material:
Church bulletins; Clippings; Correspondence; Diaries; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sermons; Williamsburg (Va.)--History--20th century
Topical Term:
Baptist Church--Virginia--History.; Baptists--United States--Clergy.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Mss. Acc. 1999.07 (Sermons and The Spire Bulletin)
  Sermons.
  These folders contain sermon outlines on different subject matter. They were preached from the outlines by Rev. Pugh at Williamsburg Baptist Church. Also included are notebooks with the sermon titles arranged by date. The dates range from the 1950s, when Pugh took up the pulpit, to the 1980s, when he retired.
  The Spire.
    Series 1: Sermons
  - Sermons
    - Advent - Evangelism (Personal) (1)
      - Advent (1)
      - Adversity (1, 2)
      - Anniversary (1, 3)
      - Art, Christian (1, 4)
      - Authority (1, 5)
      - Baccalaureate Sermon (1, 6)
      - Baptist (1, 7)
      - Baptism (1, 8)
      - Beliefs (1, 9)
        Two folders
      - Bible (1, 10)
      - Biography - non-biblical (1, 11)
      - Biography – biblical (1, 12)
      - (Unmarked) (1, 13)
      - Book Review (1, 14)
      - Character – Personal (1, 15)
      - Children (1, 16)
      - Christ – As Lord of life (1, 17)
      - Christ – Mind(?) of (1, 18)
      - Christ – Work of (1, 19)
      - Christian Citizenship (1, 20)
      - Christian Experience (1, 21)
      - Christian Education (1, 22)
      - Christian Identity (1, 23)
      - Christian Living (1, 24)
      - Christians in the Church (1, 25)
      - Christianity – as freedom (1, 26)
      - Christianity in contemporary society (1, 27)
      - Christianity – mind of (1, 28)
      - Christianity - (blank) (1, 29)
      - Christianity – Reliance of (1, 30)
      - Christianity – As vocation (1, 31)
      - Christians (1, 32)
      - Church, Body of Christ (1, 33)
      - Church Membership (1, 34)
      - Church - Local (1, 35)
      - Church - (blank) (1, 36)
      - The Commandments (1, 37)
      - Consecration (1, 38)
      - Criticism (1, 39)
      - Cross (1, 40)
      - Culture (1, 41)
      - Death (1, 42)
      - Decision - Choice (1, 43)
      - Democracy (1, 44)
      - Devotional (1, 45)
      - Discipleship (1, 46)
      - Discipleship – Evangelistic and Missionary (1, 47)
      - Drinking (1, 48)
      - Easter (1, 49)
      - Economics (1, 50)
      - Emotional(?) factors in life (1, 51)
      - Ecumenical (1, 52)
      - Ecology (1, 53)
      - Education (1, 54)
      - Evangelism (1, 55)
      - Evangelistic (1, 56)
      - Evangelism – Personal (1, 57)
    - Evil - Problem of Evil (2)
      - Evil (2, 1)
      - Expository (2)
      - Faith-Personal (2, 3)
      - Faith (2, 4)
      - Fellowship (2, 5)
      - Forgiveness (2, 6)
      - Freedom (2, 7)
      - Friendship (2, 8)
      - Fruits of Christian living (2, 9)
      - Gifts from God (2, 10)
      - God (2, 11)
      - God in Christ (2, 12)
      - God – Concept of (2, 13)
      - God – Love of (2, 14)
      - God – Nature of (2, 15)
      - God – Purpose and Will (2, 16)
      - Grace (2, 17)
      - History – Church and Biblical (2, 18)
      - Holy Spirit (2, 19)
      - Holy Week (2, 20)
      - Home and Family (2, 21)
      - Incarnation (2, 22)
      - Influence (2, 23)
      - Inspirational (2, 24)
      - Immortality (2, 25)
      - Integrity (2, 26)
      - Jesus Christ, Person of (2, 27)
      - Jesus – Man (2, 28)
      - Jesus – Ministry (2, 29)
      - Jesus Christ – Savior (2, 30)
      - Kingdom of God (2, 31)
      - Leadership – Christian (2, 32)
      - Leadership – Responsibility as Christians (2, 33)
      - Lent (2, 34)
      - Lent and Holy Week (2, 35)
      - Lenten Series (2, 36)
      - Life and Death (2, 37)
      - Lord’s Supper – General (2, 38)
      - Lord’s Supper - liturgical (2, 39)
      - Love (2, 40)
      - Love – Christian (2, 41)
      - Man (2, 42)
      - Man – Doctrine of (2, 43)
      - Maturity (2, 44)
      - Memorial (2, 45)
      - Mental Health (2, 46)
      - Ministry (2, 47)
      - Misfortune (2, 48)
      - Miracles (2, 49)
      - Miscellaneous (2, 50)
      - Missions (2, 51)
      - Morality and Ethics (2, 52)
      - Morality (2, 53)
      - Music (2, 54)
      - Nature (2, 55)
      - New Year (2, 56)
      - Occasional (2, 57)
      - Occult (2, 58)
      - Old Year (2, 59)
      - Palm Sunday (2, 60)
      - Pastoral (?) (2, 61)
      - Pastoral Ministry (2, 62)
      - Parenthood and Personality Development (2, 63)
      - Patriotic (2, 64)
      - Personal Identity (2, 65)
      - Person of Christ (2, 66)
      - Personal Living (2, 67)
      - Philosophy of Life (2, 68)
      - Preaching (2, 69)
      - Prayer (2, 70)
      - Principles (2, 71)
      - Problem of Evil (2, 72)
    - Providence (God’s Intervention in life) - Youth and the Church (3)
      Box 3a and 3b
      Also contains 7 notebooks, which contain a chronological list of sermons and topics from 1952 to 1985.
      - Providence-God’s Intervention in life (3, 1)
      - Race Relations (3, 2)
      - Radio (3)
      - Redemption (3, 4)
      - Religion (3, 5)
      - Repentance (3, 6)
      - Respect for Persons (3, 7)
      - Responsibility (3, 8)
      - Resurrection (3, 9)
      - Rewards (3, 10)
      - Sacrifice (3, 11)
      - Salvation (3, 12)
      - Second Coming (3, 13)
      - Separation of Church and State (3, 14)
      - Science of Religion (3, 15)
      - Series (3, 16)
      - Sermon on the Mount (3, 17)
      - Sex (3, 18)
      - Sin (3, 19)
      - (Unknown) (3, 20)
      - Social work not from the… (3, 21)
      - Social Righteousness (3, 22)
      - Social (?) of Christianity (3, 23)
      - Southern Baptist Convention (3, 24)
      - Special Occasions (3, 25)
      - Stewardship (3, 26)
      - Student Sermons (3, 27)
      - Success (3, 28)
      - Thanksgiving (3, 29)
      - Theology (3, 30)
      - Trinity (3, 31)
      - Truth (3, 32)
      - Viewpoints (3, 33)
      - War and Peace (3, 34)
      - World Affairs (3, 35)
      - Words of the Christian Life (3, 36)
      - Worship (3, 37)
      - Youth (3, 38)
      - Youth and the Church (3, 39)
    Series 2: The Spire
  - The Spire
    - The Spire (4)
      Church Bulletin.
- Mss. Acc. 1999.30A Addition (Church Papers)
  Papers of Thomas Pugh directly related to Williamsburg Baptist Church.
  - (5)
      Series 1: Attendance registry cards with notes or drawings on them
    - Attendance registry cards with notes or drawings on them (5)
      Series 2: Records of sale of “The Parson’s Page”
    - Records of sale of “The Parson’s Page” (5)
      Series 3: Cards from Thomas and Mary Pugh’s 50th wedding anniversary
    - Cards from Thomas and Mary Pugh’s 50th wedding anniversary (5)
      Series 4: General Thank you notes
    - General Thank you notes (5)
  - (6)
      Series 5: Sermons, Speeches and Papers
    - Sermons, Speeches and Papers (6)
        Subseries 1: Speaking occasions in Community life
      - Speaking occasions in Community life (6, 1)
        Subseries 2: Sermons
      - Sermons (6, 2)
        Subseries 3: Sermon Manuscripts
      - Sermon Manuscripts (6, 3)
        Subseries 9: Paper on cremation
      - Paper on cremation (6, 9)
      Series 6: Correspondence
    - Correspondence (6)
        Subseries 1: Jim Windsor Correspondence
      - Jim Windsor Correspondence (6, 1)
        Subseries 2: Birthday Cards
      - Birthday Cards (6, 2)
        Subseries 4: Fathers’ Day Cards
      - Fathers’ Day Cards (6, 4)
        Subseries 5: Letters to Thomas Pugh
      - Letters to Thomas Pugh (6, 5)
        - 1940s (6, 5, 1)
        - 1950s (6, 5, 2)
        - 1960s (6, 5, 3)
        - 1970s (6, 5, 4)
        - 1980s (6, 5)
        - Letters received re: retirement (6, 5)
        - 1990s (6, 5, 7)
      Series 7: Community life
    - Community life (6)
      - Community Life (6, 8)
  - (7)
      Series 9: Printed Material in Folders
    - Printed Material in Folders (7)
      - Letters of E. Lloyd Pugh, 1992-2000 (7, 1)
      - Copies of Marriage Ceremonies Used (7, 2)
      - 2 Picture albums (7, 3)
        Includes pictures from Pugh’s service in World War II as a chaplain through to the 1990s.
      - “The Parson’s Page,” by Thomas E. Pugh (7, 4)
      Series 10: 4 sermons on magnetic tape (1/4 in)
    - 4 sermons on magnetic tape (1/4 in) (7)
      Series 11: Cards
    - Cards (7)
      - 1990s (7, 5)
      - 1980s (7, 6)
      - 1970s (7)
      - 1960s (7, 8)
      - 1950s (7, 9)
      - Prior to 1950 (7, 10)
  - (8)
    Series 12: Personal and Business Papers
  - Personal and Business Papers
    - Williamsburg Baptist Church programs (1)
    - Pugh Papers (2)
      Included a Pugh Family lineage and a biographical sketch
    - Churches (3)
    - University of Richmond (4)
    - Rotary Club (5)
    - 50th Anniversary Reception (6)
    - Biographical (7)
    - Summer Place (8)
    - Yard Sale (9)
    - Fredericksburg Property (10)
    - Community (11)
    - The Parson’s Page reviews (12)
    - Sermons: Marriage and Family Life (13)
    - Miscellany (14)
    - Churches, letters and miscellany (15)
    - Diary-Summer, 1939 (16)
    - Letters (17)
    - Letters of Recommendation (18)
    - Funeral Services and Related Materials (19)
    - Funeral Services Conducted (20)
    - Sermons (21)
    - Clergy Records of Funerals (22)
    - Services Conducted and/or Speaking occasions (23)
    - Williamsburg Baptist Conflict 1996-1999 (24)
- Mss. Acc. 1999.57A Addition (Personal Papers)
  Personal Papers
  These are papers of Thomas Pugh that are not directly related to Williamsburg Baptist Church
  - (9)
      Series 1: Pictures of the entire chaplain school from when Pugh was there during WWII
    - Pictures of the entire chaplain school from when Pugh was there during WWII (9)
      Series 2: "Our Leave in Switzerland"
    - "Our Leave in Switzerland" (9)
      Series 3: An issue of Cosmopolitan given to him by a member of the church
    - An issue of Cosmopolitan given to him by a member of the church (9)
      Series 4: Military Records and Memorabilia folder
    - Military Records and Memorabilia folder (9)
      Series 5: Various newspapers
    - Various newspapers (9)
      - Nixon’s Resignation (9)
      - 1st Apollo moon landing (9)
      - Assassination of JFK (9)
      - Hurricane Floyd (9)
  - (10)
      Series 6: Personal Papers
    - Personal Papers (10)
      - 25th anniversary of serving as pastor (10)
      - Buchanan County Va. (10)
      - Life of Mary Decker Pugh (10)
      - Life of Thomas E. Pugh (10)
        Includes a picture of Bill Clinton
      - Life of the Church (10)
      - Life in the Community (10)
      Series 7: Travel
    - Travel (10)
      - Miscellany of Ted’s Bits (10, 1)
      - Nova Scotia trip 1989 (10, 2)
      - Virginia (10, 3)
      - New England (10, 4)
      - South Carolina (10, 5)
      - Travel information-miscellaneous (10, 6)
      - Georgia (10, 7)
      - North Carolina (10, 8)
      - Blue Ridge Parkway (10, 9)
      - Maps from different trips (10)
      Series 8: Church related
    - Church related (10)
      - Peninsula Baptist Association (10, 11)
      - Drawing of Cannon Memorial Chapel, University of Richmond (10)
      - Character of the Clergy of Colonial Virginia (10)
      Series 9: Williamsburg Community Hospital and Williamsburg Community Health Foundation
    - Williamsburg Community Hospital and Williamsburg Community Health Foundation (10)
      Series 10: Concerning Pugh's Book
    - Concerning Pugh's Book (10)
      Series 11: Clippings
    - Clippings (10)
      Series 12: Mary Decker Pugh folders
    - Mary Decker Pugh folders (10)
      - Bettie Grey correspondence (10, 1)
      - Binder of papers written by Mary and Thomas (10, 2)
      - David Little correspondence (10, 3)
  - (11)
      Series 13: Personal Papers
    - Personal Papers (11)
      - Picture of “Summer home on Piankitank River across from Gwynn’s Island” (11)
      - Guest book for the 25th anniversary of Mary and Tom Pugh (11)
      - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings, drivers licenses, and other personal items (11)
      - Wedding gift registry (11)
      - Picture of Pugh in his “Wedding suit” (11)
      - Life Magazine from the Kennedy Assassination (11)
      - Life Magazine from Kennedy’s funeral (11)
      - Copy of Pugh’s parents’ marriage license (11)
  - (12)
      Series 14: Scrapbooks
    - Scrapbooks (12)
      Scrapbooks of photographs and other items. Labels include "Church," "Community," "MDP" and "TEP."
- Mss. Acc. 2000.62A Addition (Personal Papers, Memo Books)
  Personal Papers and memo books.
  Items from Pugh's days at the University of Richmond and his post-retirement years in Williamsburg. Includes Memo books from 1950-1998.
  - (13)
    - Peninsula Association History (13, 1)
    - Sermon: Reflections on politics and religion (13, 2)
    - Religious Emphasis: Mary Washington College (13, 3)
    - Race Relations (13, 4)
    - Paper on cremation (13, 5)
    - Hands (13, 6)
    - Introductory notes on The Philosopher Motse (13, 7)
    - Main Themes in the Tao The Ching (13, 8)
    - The Buddhist Parable of the Seeking Father (13, 9)
    - Motse’s Essay on “Universal Reciprocal Love” (13, 10)
    - The Christian Faith and American Science (13, 11)
    - An Outline of “Beliefs that Matter” (13, 12)
    - Church Management (13)
    - Jesus’ Conception of God… (13, 14)
    - The Christian Revelation of God through Jesus (13, 15)
    - Historical Sketch of the Peninsula Baptist Association (13, 16)
    - Williamsburg Baptist Church Pastor 1952-1981 (13, 17)
    - 1916 Flat Hat (13, 18)
    - Notes and Quotes – Miscellaneous Subjects (13, 19)
    - Miscellaneous Letters and Cards (13, 20)
    - WBC – History, etc. (13, 21)
    - WBC Miscellaneous items (13, 22)
    - Letters – Miscellaneous of Special Interest (13, 23)
    - Funeral of R. Lawrence Caldwell (13, 24)
    - Golf (13, 25)
    - Health Foundation of Wmbg. Community (13, 26)
    - Notes and Quotes (13, 27)
    - Williamsburg Community Hospital (13, 28)
- Mss. Acc. 2000.32 Addition (WHRA Speech, News Clipping)
  Copy of outline of speech given to Williamsburg Historic Records Association by Rev. Thomas Pugh in 2000. Newspaper clipping reminiscences of Williamsburg before the restoration by Mayor Henry Stryker.
- Mss. Acc. 2004.38 Addition (Mary Decker Pugh Death), 2004
  Obituaries of Mary Decker Pugh from the Daily Press, 6/22/2004 and the Virginia Gazette, 6/23/2004, Bulletin from the funeral service and a photocopy of the hymn sung at the funeral service.
- Mss. Acc. 2007.33 Addition, 1999-2002
  Williamsburg Community Hospital's resolution in honor of Thomas Pugh, plus other material relating to the Hospital. Correspondence, news clippings and other material relating to Thomas Pugh's Williamsburg activities.